Guide to the James Weldon Johnson and Grace Nail Johnson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1890-1974; Series II; 22.18; (43 boxes)
  - Notebooks
    - Notebook 1, holograph, signed, undated (Box 83, Folder 635)
      Contains notes and ideas for lyrics, titles, poems, addresses, a synopsis for the play "One night to live," etc.
    - Notebook 2, holograph, signed, 1893 (Box 83, Folder 636)
      Contains early drafts of poems, essays, notes, ideas and his descriptions of a tour by the Atlanta University Quartette (circa 1893) and letters about the Chicago World's Fair (1893 April 22).
    - Notebook 3, holograph, signed, undated (Box 83, Folder 637)
      Contains notes for song titles, prose and poems, including "The White Witch," a synopsis of his play "The Sins of the Fathers," and an expense record.
    - Notebook 4, "The Red Book," holograph, signed, undated (Box 83, Folder 638)
      Contains notes for essays, plays, aphorisms and miscellaneous thoughts.
    - Notebook 5, "Verses," holograph, signed, 1890-1898 (Box 83, Folder 639)
      Contains early drafts of poems (circa 1890-1897) some later published in his Fifty Years and Other Poems such as: "Voluptas"; "Acknowledgment"; "Class Poem, Class of 1894"; "Atlanta University"; "To Louie"; "July in Georgia"; "Ghosts in the Old Year"; "From the German of Uhland"; "A Banjo Song"; "Sleep"; "Birthday Lines"; "Sonnet, from the Spanish of Plácido"; "Prayer at Sunrise."
      Includes clippings of his address at Tuskegee Institute, as published in the Tuskegee Student (1898 January 20) and his "A Letter from an Atlanta University student teaching in the country" (1891).
    - Notebook 6, holograph, signed, undated (Box 83, Folder 640)
      Contains early drafts of poems and lyrics, including his "Mobile Mardi Gras," "Optimistic Sam," "To a Midnight Cabaret Star," and "Tropical Eyes."
    - Notebook 7, holograph, signed, 1890-1895 (Box 83, Folder 641)
      Notebook used during student years. Includes notes, drafts of essays and poems (some later published in Fifty Years and Other Poems ). With a typed list of poems laid in.
      Includes: "Prize Oration, Atlanta University, 24 May 1892"; "Voluptas"; "The Poet's Harp"; "Acknowledgment"; "Class Poem, Atlanta University, 31 March 1893"; "Eulogy, Frederick Douglass, Phi Kappa Society, 1 January 1893"; "July in Georgia"; "To Louie"; "Sonnet, The Morning Glory"; "Sonnet, The Secret"; "Thoughts Beside a Lowly Grave"; "The Midnight Bell"; "Ghosts of the Old Years"; "From the German of Uhland"; "Ode to Florida"; "A Banjo Song"; "Sonnet, Sleep"; "Birthday Lines"; "Sonnet, From the Spanish of Plácido"; "Prayer at Sunrise."
    - Notebook 8, holograph, signed, 1899-1904 (Box 83, Folder 642)
      Contains drafts and final versions of poems (some later published in Fifty Years and Other Poems ). Poems included are: "Since You Went Away"; "The Color Sergeant"; "Dat Gal O'Mine"; "Tunk"; "The Rivals"; "Answer to Prayer"; "National Hymn" [Lift Every Voice]; "The Black Mammy"; "When First We Met"; "You'se Sweet to Yo' Mammy Jes de Same"; "The Glory of the Day Was in Her Face"; "Two Sonnets to Horace Bumstead"; "Sonnet Before a Painting"; "Louisiana Lize."
    - Notebook 9, holograph, signed, undated (Box 84, Folder 643)
      Contains notes, including draft of an essay on equality, signed with initials, a news clipping, a printed pamphlet with his manuscript notes, an autograph note to his secretary and a manuscript poem "A Metrical Scheme" tipped in.
    - Notebook 10, holograph and typescript, 1913-1924 (Box 84, Folder 644)
      Contains drafts and printed versions of addresses and lectures including: "Intermarriage" (1913); "The Larger Success" (Commencement Address, Hampton Institute, June 1923); "Negro Education"; "Inter-racial Relations" (25 November 1923); "Haiti and Her People" (21 April 1922); "Address Before the Twentieth Century Club Boston, Massachusetts"; "Address Before the District of Columbia Branch, N.A.A.C.P."; "Our Democracy and the Ballot (Address at the F.H. LaGuardia Dinner, 10 March 1923)"; "Address Before the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs" (9 August 1922); "What America Owes to the Negro"; "The New Emancipation" (20 September 1924); "The Function of Agitation in Race Betterment" (14 February 1924); "Education"; "Lynching in the United States"; "Address Before the District of Columbia Branch, N.A.A.C.P." (18 March 1923); "Emancipation Address" (January 1920).
    - Notebook 11, holograph, undated (Box 84, Folder 645)
      Contains notes on thoughts and ideas, addresses and a lecture schedule laid in.
  - Other Writings
    - Report on Haiti
      - Research notes, holograph and typescript, 1920 February - May (Box 85, Folder 646)
        Author's diary and notes in four envelopes marked A, C, D, E.
      - Background material, 1920 (Box 85, Folder 647-649)
        Contains statements (typescript and typescript carbon) from others concerning Haiti in French and English. Includes autograph and typescript drafts of Louis DuPlessis's essay "Haiti et l'occupation Américaine" (which was included as part of Johnson's background notes for his Special Report to the N.A.A.C.P. on Haiti).
      - "Special Report of the [N.A.A.C.P.] Field Secretary on His Visit to Haiti", drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, circa 1920 (Box 85, Folder 650)
      - "Self-Determining Haiti"
        - Printed version, The Nation, 1920 August 28- September 25 (Box 85, Folder 651)
        - Reprints, 1920 (Box 85, Folder 652-653)
      - "The Truth About Haiti", printed versions, The Crisis, 1926 July (Box 85, Folder 654)
      - "Statement of Dr. James Weldon Johnson, Secretary, National Association for the Advancement of the [sic] Colored People, New York City", printed version, Hearings Before the Subcommittee of the Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, 1925 February 25-26 (Box 85, Folder 655)
      - Printed material related to Haiti, 1920-1931 (Box 85, Folder 656-658)
    - "Negro Silent Protest Parade. Committee," typescript carbon, signed and printed version, 1917 July 28 (Box 85, Folder 659)
      Signers of statement include James Weldon Johnson, John E. Nail and 9 others.
    - Negro Spirituals - Tentative Program, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 85, Folder 660)
      Includes lists of spirituals to be sung.
      Program suggested to the St. Louis Committee [NAACP?], with an ANS (draft) by Johnson to Mr. Tocus.
    - Autobiographical statements, typescript, circa 1931 (Box 85, Folder 661)
    - Biographical Notes, circa 1931-1935 (Box 85, Folder 662)
    - Untitled, draft, typescript, undated (Box 85, Folder 663)
      Contains short story about a Georgia mule as described in Along This Way. Written in Jacksonville, Florida.
    - "Memoranda for Prose," notes and drafts, holograph, undated (Box 85, Folder 664-665)
      Notes for "essayettes," plays, and other general thoughts and phrases, titled and untitled.
      Titles for essayettes include: "Among the Losses of Antiquity"; "Anglo-Saxon Historians"; "The Children"; "Color Scheme of Humanity"; "Cycles of Civilization"; "Defeated Conquerors"; "Effects of Criticism"; "The Failures"; "Folly of Prolonging Wretched Existence"; "Ghosts"; "The Jews"; "A Literary Person"; "Monkey Shrines"; "My Philosophy"; "Royalty"; "Churches vs. Jails"; "What Would They Say?"; and "Who are the Master Men?".
      Titles for plays include: "The Lady and the Groom"; "The Man and the Maid"; "Romantic Operetta"; and "The Sophisticated Jones".
      Titles for stories include: "Hero"; "Young Man"; and "Sa Higa de Maria".
      Titles for miscellaneous notes include: "A Pullman Car Conversation"; "Useless Gods"; and "Stray Thoughts".
    - Outline for "Pharbis", draft, holograph, undated (Box 85, Folder 666)
    - Prose, essays and stories, notes, holograph, undated (Box 85, Folder 667)
    - Comic stories, jokes, doggerel, etc., typescript, undated (Box 85, Folder 668)
    - Movie shorts, draft, holograph notes, undated (Box 85, Folder 669)
      Includes extensive notes for the poem, "The Rivals," later published in Fifty Years and Other Poems and for his plays, "Circumstantial Evidence," "Sons and Daughters," and "Do You Believe in Ghosts?"
    - Inscriptions for Richetta G. Randolph, draft, typescript, undated (Box 85, Folder 670)
      Copies of inscriptions written by Johnson in his books.
    - Notes, holograph, undated (Box 85, Folder 671)
  - Publicity
    - "Lectures by James Weldon Johnson", circa 1925 (Box 86, Folder 672-674)
      Contains brochures advertising the subjects on which Johnson lectures including: "The Race Problem and World Peace"; "The Negro's Contribution to American Civilization"; "Negro Poets and Their Poetry"; "The Creative Genius of the Negro"; "The Negro as a Factor in Politics"; "The Negro: The Test of Democracy in America"; "The Fight Against Lynching"; and "Haiti and Her People and the Policy of the United States in that Republic".
    - "Speakers of Consequence" brochure, 1933-1934 (Box 86, Folder 675)
    - "James Weldon Johnson: A Biographical Sketch" by Walter White, before 1937 (Box 86, Folder 676-678)
      Contains Viking Press pamphlets listing publications and lectures
    - "James Weldon Johnson Speaks" leaflets, 1950 (Box 86, Folder 679)
    - Musicraft leaflets, 1938 (Box 86, Folder 680)
  - Writings of Others
    - Bhêly-Quenum, Olympe. "Aimé Césaire.", circa 1962 (Box 87, Folder 681)
    - Cauvin, Emile. "Un Désastre: L'Accord du 7 Aout 1933.", 1933 October 22 (Box 87, Folder 682)
      Port-au-Prince: Imprimerie Haitienne.
    - Cushnie, L.O. "Biography." Square Deal Magazine, 1915 (Box 87, Folder 683)
      Contains biography of Johnson and letter from Cushnie.
    - Du Bois, W.E.B. "George Washington and Black Folk." The Crisis, 1932 April (Box 87, Folder 684)
    - Durand, Oswald. "Choucoune.", undated (Box 87, Folder 685)
      Holograph transcription
    - Fleming, Robert E. "Irony as a Key to Johnson's Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man." Reprinted from American Literature, 1971 March 1 (Box 87, Folder 686)
      Inscribed to Grace Nail Johnson
    - Hughes, Langston. "Air Raid Over Harlem: Scenario for a Little Black Movie." New Theatre, 1936 February (Box 87, Folder 687)
    - Maeterlinck, Maurice. Pelleas and Melisande, undated (Box 87, Folder 688)
      New York: Little Leather Library, undated
    - Miller, Loren. "The Negro and the Parties." New Masses, 1936 October 13 (Box 87, Folder 689)
    - Queen, Hallie E. "To James Weldon Johnson King Arthur Speaks", undated (Box 87, Folder 690)
    - Vega, Garcia de la. "El Indiano." Translated by Rafael Diez de la Cortina., undated (Box 87, Folder 691)
    - Waybright, Victor. "Remarks at 135th Street Branch Library, 104 West 136th Street in Honor of James Weldon Johnson's Birthday.", 1948 June 17 (Box 87, Folder 692)
    - Wilson, Ruth Danenhower. "Justifications of Slavery, Past and Present," reprinted from Phylon and "Negro Colleges of Liberal Arts," reprinted from The American Scholar, 1950-1958 (Box 87, Folder 693)
    - Wohlforth, Robert. "Dark Leader." The New Yorker, 1933 September 30 (Box 87, Folder 694)
    - Zangrando, Robert. "The N.A.A.C.P. and a Federal Anti-Lynching Bill, 1934-1940." Reprinted from The Journal of Negro History, 1965 April (Box 87, Folder 695)
      Inscribed to GNJ
- Consular Service, 1906-1912; Series III; 0.1; (1 box)
  The series is organized into two subseries: Puerto Cabella, Venezuela and Corinto, Nicaragua.
  The series contains ephemera and publications relating to Johnson's work as an American Consul in Venezuela and Nicaragua between 1906 and 1912. Both the professional and social aspects of Johnson's position are reflected in the materials, such as invitations, newspaper clippings, and copies of the Daily Consular and Trade Reports. The series also provides insight into the American presence in Latin America during the early twentieth century and particularly the early period of American intervention in Nicaragua. For example, Johnson's report of the power struggle between Conservative President Adolfo Díaz and former Minister of War General Luis Mena, which took place in 1912, illustrates the American perspective and machinations during this period in Nicaraguan history.
  - Puerto Cabella, Venezuela
    - Invitations and other ephemera relating to Johnson's post in Venezuela, 1906 (Box 88, Folder 696)
    - Clippings about Johnson's post in Venezuela, 1906 (Box 88, Folder 697)
    - Daily Consular and Trade Reports with articles quoting Johnson, 1907 (Box 88, Folder 698)
  - Corinto, Nicaragua
    - Report "Transcript of Miscellaneous Record Book of This Consulate from July 29th to November 14th, 1912", drafts, typescripts, corrected and notes (Box 88, Folder 699)
      Includes typed list of persons affiliated with the Consular Services in Puerto Cabella (Venezuela) laid into an envelope addressed to Johnson.
    - The Pan-American Magazine issue on Nicaragua with note written by Grace Nail Johnson, 1911 June (Box 88, Folder 700)
    - Clippings of Nicaragua, 1911-1912
    - Freeman, Joseph, and Scott Nearing, "Armed Intervention," draft, typescript carbon, 1924 September 30 (Box 88, Folder 700a)
      Draft of chapter of Nearing and Freeman's book Dollar Diplomacy, sent to Johnson for comment.
- National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (N.A.A.C.P.), 1917-1965; Series IV; 0.1; (1 box)
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  The series is largely comprised of ephemera relating to Johnson's work as acting Secretary and Secretary for the N.A.A.C.P.. Also included is the leather binder in which Johnson kept his notes and writings while a Field Secretary; however, during processing in 1973, these writings were removed and placed in Writings (Series II). Johnson's ongoing involvement with the N.A.A.C.P. following his resignation is also documented to a smaller degree. For example, the "Anti-Lynching Petition to President Roosevelt" contains the Johnsons' signatures and those of their circle of friends and acquaintances while living in Nashville, Tennessee.
  - Invitation, tickets, and program for Reception to Graduates of the Public Schools of Greater New York, 1917 (Box 88, Folder 701)
  - Pamphlets, tickets, brochures and poster relating to JWJ's work with the N.A.A.C.P., circa 1920 (Box 88, Folder 702)
  - JWJ's Field Secretary Leather Binder, circa 1920
  - "Statement of James Weldon Johnson," To Prevent and Punish the Crime of Lynching: Hearing Before a Subcommittee of the Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate, 69th Congress, 1st Session, printed version, 1926 February 16 (Box 88, Folder 703)
  - "Anti-Lynching Petition to President Roosevelt", circa 1935-1937 (Box 88, Folder 704)
    Includes signatures from eighteen individuals including JWJ and GNJ
  - Annual Report, 1965 (Box 88, Folder 705)
- Personal Papers, 1892-1988; Series V; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  The series is organized into six subseries: Diaries and Notebooks; Day Planners, Address Books, and Guest Books; Scrapbooks and Clippings; James Weldon Johnson Schools; James Weldon Johnson Literary Guild; and Other Papers.
  The series contains various items documenting the personal lives of the Johnsons including their marriage and relationships with family and friends. The Papers also record Johnson's activities and interests as well as his legacy.
  The Johnsons' everyday activities are recorded in their diaries, notebooks, and day planners. The series also contains items such as calling cards, stationery, driver's licenses, and other ephemera, which similarly evoke the daily lives of the Johnsons. The Johnsons' wedding invitation and other material, including physical exercises and French lessons created by Johnson for Grace Nail, document their relationship. The Johnsons' wide circle of friends, which included many prominent artists, activists, and intellectuals, is recorded in material such as address books and guest books from their homes in New York City and Great Barrington, Massachusetts.
  Johnson's interests and activities are also well represented in the series, which includes, for example, a variety of scrapbooks and clippings documenting his involvement in theatre, politics, and civil rights. These scrapbooks and clippings illustrate Johnson's desire to record particular topics and events which were often intertwined with his writings and other professional activities.
  Various documents in the series record honours bestowed on James Weldon Johnson. For example, material in the subseries James Weldon Johnson Literary Guild provides evidence of a Guild created in 1931 in honour of the author (original members include a number of literary figures such as Dr. Molly Lewis, Miss Roberta Bosley, Zora Neale Hurston, Oliva Hunter, Alberta Revallion, Mae Cowderly, Harriet Pickens, and Dorothy West). Similarly, material relating to Johnson's funeral and memorials, including Gene Buck's eulogy, a scrapbook of tributes, schools named in honour of Johnson, and a commemorative stamp, illustrate Johnson's enduring legacy.
  - Diaries and Notebooks
    - Diaries, 1929 (Box 89, Folder 706)
      Two notebooks, one bound, one looseleaf, with entries by Johnson and his wife, holograph notes laid in.
    - Diary, undated (Box 89, Folder 707)
    - Notebook belonging to GNJ, 1918 (Box 89, Folder 708)
    - Notes made by GNJ, undated (Box 89, Folder 709)
  - Day Planners, Address Books, and Guest Books
    - Day Planners, 1922-1938 (Box 89, Folder 710-713)
      There are no day planners for: 1929-1930, 1932-1933, 1935, and 1937.
    - Day Planners, 1922-1938 (Box 90, Folder 714)
    - Address Books, undated (Box 90, Folder 715)
    - Guest book, New York, NY, 1923-1931 (Box 90, Folder 716)
      Bound notebook with signatures of guests visiting the Johnsons at 187 W 135 St.
    - Guest book, Great Barrington, Mass., 1931-1950 (Box 90, Folder 717)
      Bound notebook with signatures of guests visiting the Johnsons at Five Acres.
    - Guest lists, 1938 (Box 90, Folder 718)
      One notebook listing house guests in Nashville, Tennessee, and two notebooks signed by those attending JWJ's funeral.
  - Scrapbooks and Clippings
    Some loose correspondence was removed from the scrapbooks and filed in the Correspondence Series.
    - General Scrapbooks
      - 1892-1895
        Includes clippings from The Daily American
      - 1906-1919
      - 1915-1917
      - 1917-1930
      - 1928-1930
      - 1929-1933
      - 1929-1930
      - 1930-1936
      - 1931-1937
        Scrapbook created by Ollie Jewell Sims for James Weldon Johnson
    - Topical Scrapbooks
      - "The Colored Brother by H.L. Mencken", 1927
      - "The Colored Players", 1917
        Clippings largely of Mrs. Emilia Hapgood in Three Plays by Ridgely Torrence at the Garden Theatre.
      - "Dr. W. E. Burghardt DuBois", 1934
      - "First Quadrennial Institute on Human Relations", 1927
      - "Florence Mills", 1927
      - "The Green Pastures", 1930
      - "Harmon Award", 1926-1928
      - "William E. Harmon Awards for Distinguished Achievement Among Negroes", 1930
        Directions to Judges in Field of Literature
      - "Institute of Pacific Relations", 1929
      - "James Weldon Johnson Testimonial Dinner", 1931
      - "James Weldon Johnson at Fisk University", 1931-1933
      - "Louis Marshall", 1929
      - "Magazine Articles", circa 1917-1932
      - "Miscellaneous Clippings", 1917-1936
      - "Music and Art", 1926 February - 1927 August
      - "Music and Art", 1927 September - 1928 July
      - "Poems by Negroes Including James Weldon Johnson", 1923-1924
      - "Political Campaign 1928", 1928-1929
      - "Rev. William S. Blackshear (Discrimination in Church)", 1929
      - "School Blacklist", 1926
      - "Soviet Russia by Eugene Lyons", 1931
      - "Spingarn Medal", 1925
      - "The Stage", 1905-1910
      - "The Stage", 1917-1930
      - "The Stage", 1926-1927
      - "The Stage", 1931-1933
      - "The Stage", 1897-1912
        Scrapbook created by Stella Wiley gifted to JWJ while he was writing Black Manhattan.
      - Scrapbook of Jesse Owens, 1936
      - Scrapbook of tributes to James Weldon Johnson compiled by Lucile V. Miller and Grace Nail Johnson, 1938
        Includes photographs of Johnsons visiting Anna and George Payne and Grace Nail Johnson in hospital; newspaper clippings about accident and Johnson's funeral; and material related to various commemorations in honor of James Weldon Johnson.
      - "Theatre Clippings", 1925-1930
    - Loose Clippings
      - Clippings about JWJ and GNJ, circa 1916-1972 (Box 90, Folder 719-720)
      - Clippings about friends and family, circa 1917-1984 (Box 90, Folder 721-722)
      - Clippings on various topics collected by JWJ and GNJ, circa 1900-1960 (Box 90, Folder 723)
      - Lists of scrapbook contents created by the Beinecke Library and Grace Nail Johnson, circa 1996 (Box 90, Folder 723a)
        For scrapbooks formerly catalogued as JWJ ZAN J632 + ZC1
  - James Weldon Johnson Schools
    - Chicago, Illinois
      - Invitations, 1963 (Box 91, Folder 724)
    - New York, New York
      - Ephemera relating to the building and dedication of the school including newsletters, invitations, programs, correspondence, and photographs, 1964-1966 (Box 91, Folder 725-726)
      - Audio recordings of school children performing "Lift Every Voice and Sing" and "The Creation", 1966 (Box 91, Folder 727-728)
  - James Weldon Johnson Literary Guild
    - Scrapbook, 1940-1953
    - Meeting minutes and constitution, 1949 (Box 91, Folder 729)
    - Newsletters, 1949-1952 (Box 91, Folder 730)
    - Writings by and about Guild members, 1945-1959 (Box 91, Folder 731)
    - Invitations and photograph of JWJ, 1957 (Box 91, Folder 732)
  - Other Papers
    Arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Certificates, diplomas, and membership cards, 1897-1938 (Box 91, Folder 733)
      Includes teaching certificate, certificate acknowledging admittance to the Florida bar, diplomas from University of Atlanta and Howard University, certificate inviting JWJ to participate in inauguration parade for Theodore Roosevelt.
    - Invitation to the Johnsons' wedding, 1910 (Box 91, Folder 734)
    - Exercises created by JWJ for GNJ, holograph, 1910 (Box 91, Folder 735)
      Includes autograph note by Grace Nail Johnson concerning the origin of this manuscript
    - Driver's licenses, passport, visa, and military census, 1917-1936 (Box 91, Folder 736)
    - Invitations, 1919-1948 (Box 91, Folder 737)
    - Blueprints for the Johnsons' home "Five Acres" in Great Barrington, Massachusetts by J. Mc.A. Vance, circa 1926
      Includes eight blueprints
    - Floor plans for "Five Acres" in Great Barrington, Massachusetts, circa 1926 (Box 91, Folder 738)
    - Receipts, brochures, and pamphlets from JWJ's trip to Japan, 1929 (Box 91, Folder 739)
    - List of books written by Johnson, circa 1930 (Box 91, Folder 740)
    - Invitation and other ephemera related to dinner in honor of JWJ, 1931 (Box 91, Folder 741)
    - Diet list for JWJ, 1931 (Box 91, Folder 742)
    - Luggage tags for JWJ, circa 1932 (Box 91, Folder 743)
    - Schedules for lecture tours, 1933-1934 (Box 91, Folder 744)
    - List of books in the Johnsons' library at their home in Nashville and list of books in the Francis Collection, 1934 (Box 91, Folder 745)
      Includes note from Ollie Jewell Sims Okala about library
    - Inscriptions to EBJ and TEJ, circa 1934 (Box 91, Folder 746)
      Initials possibly refer to Esther A. Balderston Jones and Thomas Elsa Jones
    - Memoranda and lists of individuals and addresses, 1936, undated (Box 91, Folder 747)
    - Ticket stubs, 1937, 1956 (Box 91, Folder 748)
    - Maps of Maine and notes by GNJ and Carl Van Vechten, 1938 (Box 92, Folder 749)
      Route between Great Barrington (MA.) and Maine highlighted